Today's דף daf is למד, Lamed, but we are
picking up on כ"ט עמוד ב' Kaf-Tet Amud Bet at the very
top. Exactly. We are doing on the משנה Mishnah that speaks about
פרשיות parshiyot of the מזוזה mezuzah מעכב, ma'akev, but the משנה Mishnah
said even one letter. So we're talking about what does that mean
one letter? Because it's taken for granted that if one letter is
missing it's no good, and so it's coming to tell you some
of the very specific requirements. For example, there's a requirement called מוקף
גויל, mukaf gvil, that it has to be surrounded by parchment. It
cannot be connected to the letters nearby.
So therefore for that, the גמרא Gemara says however that's sort of
the outer perimeter of the letter. If there's a hole smack in
the middle of the הא, Hei, so that the little leg of
the הא, Hei, you know, the two inner legs are not touching
parchment, they're touching the hole, that's kosher, because מוקף גויל mukaf gvil
is about the area around it. And then it said that what
about if some of the letter is broken? So like it says
like the leg, the outer leg of the הא Hei is actually
broken, or even the inner like, you know, the inner little leg
but it's not just that it's touching a hole, it's that it's
not actually a full line. So the גמרא Gemara says it has
to look like an אות קטנה, ot ktana, the smallest letter which
means like a יוד. Yud. There's actually some debate, the ראש Rosh
says that they're talking about the sort of,
you know, the large leg of the הא, Hei, the right leg,
that has to look like the יוד, Yud, but if the inner
leg is enough that it's even a tiny little dot, that's what
the ראש Rosh says. Many other ראשונים Rishonim say even the inner
leg has at least be the size of the יוד. Yud.
Yeah, I remember כחצי יוד,
K'atzit Yud, inner leg?
Yeah. Well, it depends about how big is your יוד? Yud? But
okay, but of the same font, I assume is the point.
Okay, טוב. tov. And so the גמרא Gemara had that discussion, we're
going to continue with some of those issues. And again, the point
is other than the גמרא Gemara we saw that the קוצו של
יוד, kutzoh shel Yud, which again might mean the red leg, the
right leg which is obvious or might mean the kind of little
dot at the top, no, in general the גמרא Gemara does not
give very much in terms of the exact details of what a
letter has to look like. It's more it have to look like
the letter, what we are familiar with the letter. We're about to
see in a minute about even asking a small boy to, you
know, recognize it. Nevertheless, there are other criteria like it had to
be surrounded with גויל, gvil, it had to, you know, if it's
cut short, it's not going down the full length, at what stage
is that still considered the letter and so on. But there's not
like a big table,
if we look in the משנה
ברורה Mishnah
Berurah there on הלכות תפילין, Hilkhot Tefillin, you will see that he
sort of goes letter by letter and believe me, if you were
learning from a סופר sofer you'd see even more. So he actually
here, you know, goes like this whole thing about, you know, every
single letter, this is in סימן ל"ו, Siman Lamed-Vav, you know, here's
what an אלף Alef has to look like, here's what a בית
Bet has to look like, here's what a גימל Gimmel has to
look like. Of course it's a little hard without pictures. There actually
I thought was some pictures somewhere in the back with this. But
anyway, but regardless,
the גמרא Gemara does not give you most of, yeah, yeah, well
that's the גמרא Gemara and תוספות. Tosafot. The גמרא Gemara does not
give you most of those details. So let's keep on looking. One
interesting one was this idea of the קוצו kutzoh of the יוד.
Yud. So now four lines from the top on כ"ט עמוד ב'.
Kaf-Tet Amud Bet. רמי בר חמי דהוא חמוה דרמי בר דיקולי, Rami
bar Khami dehu khamuya deRami bar Dikuli, רמי Rami the son of
חמי, Khami, which mean of course dates, who is the father-in-law of
רמי Rami the son of דיקולי, Dikulei, which of course means a
date palm. So
I wonder if their names had anything to do with marrying into
the family or maybe it was
once he married into the family he changed his name? I don't
know. Anyway,
איפסקיה כרעא דואו, ifsakei kara d'vav,
so the leg of the ואו Vav was broken in the word
of ויהרג, Vayeharog, which is in the פסוק pasuk of with one
of the four פרשיות parshiyot of תפילין, Tefillin, it says, you know,
God smote all of the
firstborn, so ויהרג ויהרג ויהרג, Vayeharog Vayeharog Vayeharog, let me be right,
maybe ויהרג. Vayeharog. Okay anyway, בנקבא, b'nikba,
with a hole. אתא לקמיה דרבי זירא, ata lakamei d'Rabbi Zeira, he
came to Rabbi Zeira. אמר ליה זיל אייתי ינוקא דלא חכים ולא
טיפש. amar lei zil aytei yanuka d'lo khakhim v'lo tipesh. Go get
a child that's not too smart and not too average intelligence, right,
not too smart because you don't want him to figure out by
context what the word is and it's not really just by what
the letters look like. And not too dumb because you want him
to have a sense of what the letters should look like, okay.
אי קרי ליה ויהרג כשר, i kari lei Vayeharog kosher, he reads
it like it should be, it's kosher. אילו, ilo, if he doesn't
read it that way, then
יהרג הוא ופסול. Yeherog hu v'pasul. The ואו Vav would be like
a יוד Yud and it would be invalid. Now this is specifically
with the issue that the leg of the ואו Vav might not
be long enough and is it a ואו, Vav, is it a
יוד? Yud? There are other types of things which are clear formal
invalidities and the תינוק tinok doesn't matter what it looks like. If
it's not מוקף גויל, mukaf gvil, if it's touching a neighboring letter,
I don't care what a little boy, you know, or you know,
says about what it looks like, it's touching another letter. But if
there's a question about well, is this long enough to be considered
a ואו Vav or maybe it's so small it's a יוד, Yud,
a lot of that has to do with what does it look
like? So I'll just tell you this is a major area of
הלכה, Halakha, you know, sometimes this will happen, there'll be some question
in the שול shul and they'll bring up some little kid, that
boy, could be a girl, sometimes they block out. the surrounding words
or letters so it shouldn't be influenced by interpreting it by context.
Okay. But the big question is what types of things is it
just a question of does it look like it that you want
to get sort of an innocent opinion of whether it looks like
it and what types of things are possible formal invalidities? So I
just want to read you very briefly, we're not going to have
that full discussion now, but just to give you a little bit
of sense, I want to read to you how this is ruled
in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, this same הלכה Halacha about getting
a minor to come in and read it.
If he's a minor it could be someone who doesn't have a
bunch of education. Right, that's true.
Yes, that is correct.
Okay, so because like
this, נפסקה אחת מהאותיות, nifsaka achat mei'ha'otiyot, if one of the letters
is broken, and the רמא Rema says הפשוטות, ha'peshutot, which is like
basically like a straight thing like a וו vav or a זיין
zayin or the or what, yeah like it's like a, yeah meaning
it doesn't have to be a hole, it could just be like
the ink broke and it's not a straight line of ink. Okay.
אם תינוק שאינו לא חכם ולא טיפש יודע לקרותו כשר, im tinok
she'eino lo chacham v'lo tipesh yodea l'korato kasher, if read by a
minor of this type, ואם לא פסול, v'im lo pasul, and then
he says ואין צריך לכסות לו שאר אותיות כמו שנוהגין, v'ein tzarich
l'chasot lo shear otiyot kmo she'nohagin, you don't have to cover up
the other letters although that's the practice, you don't really have to
do that. Okay, and then the רמא Rema says מיהו אם אנו
רואים שלא ניכר צורת האות כתיקונו פסול אף על פי שהתינוק קוראו
כהוגן. mihu im anu ro'im shelo nikar tzurah ha'ot k'tikuno pasul af
al pi she'hatinok kora'o k'hogen. If we see that it doesn't look
officially like the letter, even if the child can identify it, it's
not good. Okay, and so again you see this tension between is
there a formal rule or is it about what does it look
like? So we're saying well if we're not sure get a child,
but of course if we know it's not the letter, well how
do we know?
And then it says, I mean what is everyone acting like? There's
two lines of שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and this amount of commentary
on this דף, daf, all right. So what what
goes into this?
Well you know it's the range of judgment call.
Right, there's a certain point where even if he guesses it right,
oh the question is is he guessing or is he right? So
maybe that's what the רמא Rema meant, it was a good guess
but we know that it's not really. You know there's no other
letter, got to be this, looks closest to this.
If it's formal, I mean I'm already thinking you know which parent
is going to be happy that their child was chosen as the
average.
All right, anyway then one more הלכה halacha in the שולחן ערוך,
Shulchan Aruch, one more law he says, הא דמכשירינן כשנפסק אות דוקא
כשנכתב בכשרות ואחר כך נפסק. ha de'machshirinan keshenifsak ot davka keshenichtav b'kashrut
v'achar kach nifsak.
This is when it was originally written כשר kosher and then either
something, there was a hole or the ink broke or something afterwards.
אבל אם מתחלה כשנכתב היה שם נקב ונפסק בו או אם רגלו
של כף פשוטה וכיוצא בה מגעת לסוף הקלף בלא היקף קלף מתחילתו
פסול. aval im mitchilah keshenichtav hayah sham nekev v'nifsak bo o im
raglo shel chaf peshutah v'chayotze bah magaat l'sof ha'klaf belo heikef klaf
mitchilato pasul.
But now this is a problem about מוקף גויל mukaf gvil because
here he's talking about there's a hole. So a hole is only
okay if it happens afterwards, but if the hole was there beforehand,
then it would never have been מוקף גויל mukaf gvil because the
end of the ink would have been touching a hole and not
touching קלף. klaf. Okay, so you have to make sure it was
written originally correctly and it was מוקף גויל, mukaf gvil, then a
hole came, is it still the letter? Let's get a minor to
check, but we have to make we have to double check what
the minor is saying and make sure you know that it really
can be considered the letter. Very famous area of הלכה. halacha. That
was in Huntington where
they had to close five ספרי תורה Sifrei Torahs in one morning.
Oh my gosh, five? Wow. Okay,
that's probably a בעל קורא baal korei knew too much. I there
was a I was once... They didn't call it Huntington.
Interesting. And I thought there were six תורות. Torahs.
I knew I know of a guy that they would never give
him an עליה aliyah because every time they gave him an עליה
aliyah he'd find a פסול pasul in the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
so finally it was like a יום טוב Yom Tov they didn't
give him an עליה aliyah so they had רחמנות rachmanus and they
gave him הגבהה. hagbah. So as he's doing הגבהה hagbah he said
oh I see...
All right, anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav, Rav Yehudah
says in the name of Rav. So now we talked before about
Moshe's difficulty with the מנורה, Menorah, now we get one of the
most famous גמרות Gemaras which is also a מדרש Midrash in שבת
Shabbat and אגדתא Aggadata in שבת. Shabbat. בשעה שעלה משה למרום, B'shaah
she'alah Moshe lamarom, when Moshe went up to the heavens to get
the תורה, Torah, מצאו להקדוש ברוך הוא שיושב וקושר כתרים לאותיות. matza'o
le'ha'Kadosh Baruch Hu she'yoshev v'kosher k'tarim l'otiyot. He found God tying crowns
to the letters. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, now what are these crowns?
We're going to see in a minute if you see in the
תוספות Tosafot there's a little thing by the זיין, zayin, these are
being special little crowns that are put on the letters of the
שעטנז גץ, shaatnez gets, שין, shin, עין, ayin, טית, tet, נון, nun,
זיין, zayin, גימל, gimel, צדי, tzadi,
whether they are the middle letters or the end letters they get
little three-pointed crowns. There's questions how exactly they're spread out. You see
in תוספות Tosafot one example is one of the actually actual sticks
goes down, we don't say that all three go up, but they're
spread over the top of the letter. We basically say that the
three little sticks that go up that make the crown all come
at the edge of the letter... what?
Like no, not like the זיין, zayin, no, take a look here.
Well a little bit, but not as spread out as they are
there. This is I wrote I thought I'm sorry I didn't get
a chance I'll upload it to the to the blog there so
you
share three not but not as spread out as they are there.
This is, I forgot, I'm sorry, I didn't get a chance to
help upload it to the blog there.
So here are three different examples of כתב Ksav and
you can take a look. I don't know why they put this
פסוק Pasuk of שם השם Shem HaShem in here so this is
שמות. Shaimos. Anyway, you can take a look, the נונס Nuns get
it, the נון סופית, Nun Sofit, right, the עינס Ayins get it,
the שינס, Shins, the גימלס. Gimmels. So actually this does is really
much like centered, the עין Ayin is a good example, it's really
much centered in
the, the middle top is the high one and then the two
others come sort of close by, not exactly like the Tosafos that
we have. Okay, so three different examples of כתב Ksav but they're
all pretty similar in terms of how they make these things which
are called
קרין.
Karin.
I wonder if there's an equivalent to the 'Quick brown fox jumps
over the lazy dog'.
Yeah,
I have no idea why they picked this פסוק Pasuk of all
things, especially I would have picked a פסוק Pasuk that didn't have
שם השם Shem HaShem in it. It's not a פסוק Pasuk in
the תורה Torah anyway. Okay, so now let's take a look. So
משה Moshe went up and saw God tying the crowns to the
letters. אמר לפניו, Amar Lefanav, he said to him, רבונו של עולם,
Ribbono Shel Olam, Master of the Universe, מי מעכב על ידך, Mi
Me'akev Al Yadecha, who's holding back your hand? Now that's a very
funny phrase. What do you mean holding back his hand? Actually his
hand isn't being held back, his hand is tying the, tying the
crowns to letters, but presumably what it means is who's preventing you
from giving the תורה Torah already? Like give it already, all the
letters are written, who's stopping you from giving it now? Why do
you have to spend your time putting on these crowns? אמר לו,
Amar Lo, so God said to משה, Moshe, אדם אחד יש שעתיד
להיות בסוף כמה דורות, Adam Echad Yesh She'asid Lihyos Besof Kama Doros,
there's one person who will be at the end of many generations,
ועקיבא בן יוסף שמו, Va'Akiva Ben Yosef Shemo, his name is עקיבא
Akiva the son of יוסף, Yosef, רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, שעתיד לדרוש
על כל קוץ וקוץ, She'asid Lidrosh Al Kol Kotz V'Kotz,
there you have the קוץ, Kotz, the קוץ Kotz of the י',
Yud, who is in the end going to interpret on every little
jot and tittle is how we would say, קוץ וקוץ, Kotz V'Kotz,
תילי תילים Tili Tilim של הלכות, Shel Halachos,
mountains and mountains of laws he will learn out from every little
jot and tittle. So that's why, עקיבא Akiva is holding me back.
I gotta put on these little crowns so he'll be able to
interpret it. I have to tell you what's fascinating about this. Do
we see עקיבא Akiva that he does it anywhere in the entire
תורה? Torah? No, he more דורש Darshens an extra 'את' Es or
'גם' Gam not actually the and that's a good point because it's
a little bit of a problem here. If there were like a
more arbitrary or random assignment of the crowns you could say that
every crown has something to learn out from it. But is it
a fixed system? You do it on very specific letters then how
can you use it as a basis for דרש? Drash? You know,
you can totally predict it. So every גימל's Gimmel gonna get it,
every נון's Nun gonna get it. So that part of the reason
why we don't find רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva doing it. So I
don't know, there's gotta be a good like דרש Drash here about
like this אגדתא Aggadta about what that means. Probably what it means
and this is I think the major theme of this which we're
gonna see is the power of the human creativity and what it
means about our partnership in תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al Peh that
even to a certain degree if the, you know, if it's not,
it's not intrinsically meaningful, you can't say that every one of the
קרין Karin is intrinsically meaningful because we know where it's going to
appear. Okay, but nevertheless part of what God does by giving us
over the ability to be part of תורה שבעל פה Torah Sheba'al
Peh is that we can infer things even if they're not פשט
Pshat exactly. You know which is sort of always up to you,
even if that's not really what בורא Borei meant, if I'm gonna
put a little כתר Keser and get them, I'm gonna say that's
what it means over here. And that of course was the power
of רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. Now I don't know if we ever
find him doing it with the crowns, but that's his power, that
he is able to learn anything out of it. It could be
a metaphor. Yeah, exactly. Okay.
When
was it when they saw it like in the ancient documents?
Oh, that's a very good question. How far back do the crowns
go?
Yeah, and in the Dead Sea Scrolls we definitely have that. I'll
look up, yeah.
Oh no, we have pictures.
No, we definitely have scrolls. I'll look it up, I'll look it
up. That's a great question. I don't know. We do know and
when we get to learning תפילין Tefillin that there's a debate of
רש''י Rashi and רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam about how the פרשיות Parshiyos
are ordered in the תפילין Tefillin and both versions were found in,
were found in Masada. Okay, so about these things I'm sure we
know, I just don't know right now.
But wouldn't you say if they were back in ancient times they
wouldn't look exactly
at the time of
סיני, Sinai, the letters looked differently.
Correct, correct. Which the בבלי Bavli does not acknowledge, but the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi does. Okay, so let's keep on going. אמר לפניו, Amar Lefanav,
so he said to him, רבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, הראני,
Hareini, show him to me. Show him to me. אמר לו, Amar
Lo, so he said, חזור לאחורך, Chazor Leachorecha, look go behind yourself,
which is also a suggestive phrase but probably means at any rate
'sit down', it means 'turn around'. הלך וישב בסוף שמונה שורות, Halach
Veyashav Besof Shmoneh Shuros,
so he went into רבי עקיבא's Rebbi Akiva classroom and he sat
at the back of the eight rows. ולא היה יודע מה הן
אומרים, Velo Hayah Yodea Mah Hen Omrim, so he didn't know what
they were talking about. They were learning הלכה Halacha that didn't seem
too familiar to him. He thought he knew the תורה, Torah, that's
why he had to be sent to the back of the class.
Okay. תשש כחו, Tashash Kocho,
so he felt very weak, he was sort of a little despondent.
כיון שהגיע לדבר אחד, Keivan Shehigia Ledavar Echad, when he came to
one particular הלכה, Halacha, אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru Lo Talmidav,
the students of רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva said to him, רבי מנין לך, Rebbi Minayin Lach,
Rabbi, where do you learn this from? אמר להן, Amar Lahen, he
said to them, הלכה
למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, oh it's a tradition going all the
way back to משה. Moshe. נתיישבה דעתו, Nisyashvah Da'ato, now he felt
better. So I think, you know, there's a fascinating discussion and I
was trying to look up some classic, you know, commentators of the
אגדתא Aggadata what they did with this,
because, you know, like why, how is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva different
than משה, Moshe, why was it given to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and not given to משה, Moshe, or not given to משה, Moshe,
I mean why was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva able to do this
and not משה? Moshe? And there were some interesting answers to that.
Like for example, there was one from the מי השילוח Mei HaShiloach
I think that says that he tried to, when we think of
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, I think of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, I
think of him like I said as this tremendous human creativity of
תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBaal Peh and inferring הלכות. halakhot. For some
reason he identified with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in the מי השילוח
Mei HaShiloach the idea that he made a lot of תקנות takkanot
and גזירות דרבנן. gezeirot d'rabbanan. I never associate that with רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and there are other rabbis who make a lot of
גזירות. gezeirot. Anyway, so he said that's why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
had all of these laws because he was making all of these
safeguards. And that, you know, that the תורה Torah was trying to
express a difference basically about how does one focus on one's Judaism:
does one focus on doing the right and not so much worry
about protecting against doing the wrong, or does one focus on, you
know, protecting against the wrong? He sort of said it was between
the אנכי ה' אלהיך Anochi Hashem Elokecha versus the לא יהיה לך.
lo yihiyeh lecha. So he said that's why when they got to
משה Moshe was the אנכי ה' אלהיך Anochi Hashem Elokecha but רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that's how he framed it if you want, sort
of the idea that Rabbinic Judaism has a lot of safeguards. And
then he said that when they got to דבר אחד, davar echad,
so he says that דבר אחד davar echad is the unity of
God, אנכי ה' אלהיך, Anochi Hashem Elokecha, that ultimately he attributed back
to משה. Moshe. Alright, it's an interesting דרש, drash, but I think
it takes us far afield from what's really going on here. And
what's really going on here seems to be, you know, a powerful
Rabbinic acknowledgment of the idea of תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBaal Peh
and how if somebody like משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu himself were to
come down and sit in our דף יומי Daf Yomi שיעור shiur
and look at this גמרא, Gemara, he wouldn't recognize what we were
talking about because that is the power of תורה שבעל פה Torah
SheBaal Peh is that we interpret and infer and that רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, תלי תלים של הלכות, tili tilim shel halakhot, which were
not necessarily the original intent, but that's what the nature of the
partnership is, is that we are part of that process of continuing
to interpret and develop to the point that משה Moshe can't understand
what's going on, but in the end it all sources itself back
to משה. Moshe. הלכה למשה מסיני, Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai, that it all
goes back to the תורה Torah that משה Moshe gave and that's
the relationship.
And thus having said that, משה Moshe is satisfied. He still doesn't
understand all the דרש drash but he's satisfied because he knows he's
the source, he's the given source. And the question that was raised
that you raised was why didn't משה Moshe have all this? And
the point is משה Moshe had a lot to do.
Right. Well, you know, it's like the kid that, it's like
the parent that the kid doesn't know, you know, doesn't know his
presidents and the parent says, "When I was your age I knew
all of the presidents by heart." He says, "Well, when you were
my age there were only three or four."
So when משה, Moshe, you didn't need a huge תורה שבעל פה
Torah SheBaal Peh yet. As time progressed you needed the
תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBaal Peh to continue to grow. Okay, so
that's why, you know, the גמרא, Gemara, well that's also what he
did sometimes. Anyway, נתיישבה דעתו, nityashva da'ato, but he
was not that he felt better because, I mean so רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is still saying all he had to say, but he
understands that it's all part of the
tradition, right, that it's not a new thing, it's just a development.
Right, exactly, exactly. Okay, so alright, to that's why God is writing
these... and by the way there's a... רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe
Feinstein in his introduction אגרות משה Igros Moshe focuses on this גמרא
Gemara and talks about the power of a פוסק, posek, that a
פוסק posek if he goes through his responsibility
correctly with real integrity and looking at all the sources, then he
doesn't have to be afraid that the פסק psak is incorrect because
by definition the פסק psak is correct. That's the idea of תורה
שבעל פה Torah SheBaal Peh is that, you know, even if you
continue to develop or whatever, if you do it with a search
for truth and with integrity and with precedence and the sources and
whatever you say ultimately will be the תורה Torah that God wants
and that's how he sort of says that's what's going on here
with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and משה, Moshe, what רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says ultimately becomes God's תורה. Torah. So he says it's a
beautiful, you know, introduction to his אגרות משה, Igros Moshe, yeah.
I notice this is just, you know, some is speculation, but don't
you get the feeling that משה Moshe felt a sense of joy
that whatever was created at his time kept growing?
Well,
no, once he understood that they were ultimately acknowledging this as a
development and it was נתיישבה דעתו. nityashva da'ato. The question is how
did he feel after נתיישבה דעתו? nityashva da'ato? Did he make his
peace with it or was he actually happy with it? That's not
so clear. Okay, נתיישבה דעתו nityashva da'ato sounds a little more like
he made his peace with it, yes.
Why does it say turn around when you're looking into the future?
Yeah, so that is a
good question and especially since the whole idea is about how it
continues to develop in the future.
It could be because he goes immediately to the back of the
class. He doesn't say like he starts at the front row and
keeps on getting back, moving back, until he went straight to the
eighth row. So to me it's like you have to actually take
a step back, you're not Mr. Big Shot anymore, חזור לאחוריך, chazor
leachorecha, like, you know, you have to actually you're going to go
to the back of the class and understand that sort of in
certain ways, you know, a lot of what ultimately becomes authoritative is
how it's interpreted after you and not ultimately you.
So that's how I would
read the just saying.
The idea that of saying that it's תורה למשה מסיני Torah l'Moshe
miSinai
when it isn't anymore. Right?
Right. But it is. Those
are the sources of that.
That's why he came from something that that was. He said, where
do you know the source is this, I don't have a drasha
for it, it's the tradition. But I think the point is like
I was trying to say before, excuse me, that even if some
of it is new, but at least like imagine Moshe comes in
there and they're teaching a different different Torah than he never heard
of before. So, he thinks all his work was for nothing. But
when he understands that its its the root is his root and
it's the tradition.
Right. No, בשיטה אחרת, B’shita acheret, although that one thing was, then
other things that it wasn't.
Yeah, well, I didn't understand. I understood הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe
miSinai and says this one thing of הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe
miSinai but that framed everything. It's all ultimately, look, it's when we
say the right of privacy, there's a constitutional right of privacy. You
know, there isn't a constitutional right of privacy. Since the Supreme Court
decided that there was a constitutional right of privacy, and now there's
a constitutional right of privacy. So, you know, that ultimately is it
is תורת משה. Toras Moshe. Its authority comes from the fact that
it comes from God and it came communicated to Moshe. But now
whatever we interpret, right, but the actual content of the...
right, right.
That's a very interesting paradox, right?
Yes.
Okay, well, that's the question of whether he was happy or just
מיושב דעתו. Mityashev da'ato. But let's keep on going. So, הגמרא Hagemara
says...
okay. Where are we? חזר ובא לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. Chazar u'va
lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu. Then he returned to God. אמר לפניו, Amar
lefanav, רבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, יש לך אדם כזה ואתה
נותן תורה על ידי? Yesh lecha adam kaze v'ata noten Torah al
yadai? You have a person such as this and I'm the one
you're giving the Torah to? Now, of course, the great best answer
is, of course, because you're actually the one that's supposed to be
the perfect vessel of just getting the words down. We don't want
your creativity. And he's the one that's going to come later for
his creativity. So, I'm serious. It's like what Shaul Lieberman said about
the role of the תנאים, Tannaim, the multi-tannaim, the memorizers that they
had for the Mishnah. That set they said, you wanted people with
great memories and no creativity because you wanted them just to memorize
it and repeat it and not insert themselves.
But anyway, the expression comes to Judaism for exactly that.
So, Moshe said, so why are you giving it to me?
So, אמר לו, Amar lo, שתוק. Shtok. Quiet. כך עלה במחשבה לפני.
Kach ala b'machshava lefanai. This is my this was my intent. This
was this was my game plan. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, רבונו של
עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, הראיתני תורתו, He’reitni Torato, הראני
שכרו. He’reini secharo. Show me his Torah, show me his reward. אמר
לו, Amar lo, חזור לאחוריך. Chazor l’achorecha. Go back, turn around. It's
again that there's that turn around imagery. There's got to be something
about this turning around imagery more than more. I agree with Rachel.
Anyway, חזור לאחוריו, Chazor l’achorav, he looked behind him. ראה ששוקלין בשרו
במקולין. Ra'a sheshoklin b'saro b'makulin.
They saw the Romans weighing out the meat of Rabbi Akiva's corpse
in like the butcher stores. Meaning he was martyred. You know, they
turned him into meat.
So, אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, so Moshe said to God, רבונו של
עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, זו תורה וזו שכרה? Zu Torah v’zu sechara?
This is the Torah
and this is its reward? אמר לו, Amar lo, שתוק. Shtok. Quiet.
כך עלה במחשבה לפני. Kach ala b'machshava lefanai.
So, it was the intent before me. So, again, a very interesting
parallel with the other intent. Some things are arbitrary. You can't understand.
Ultimately, it's part of the divine plan. Same way you don't understand
why Rabbi Akiva was not given the Torah, you can't understand why
this is his reward. Now, I do want to say that this
is also, besides being a very powerful מדרש Midrash about the nature
of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she'be'al peh, it's an extremely powerful מדרש
Midrash about theodicy and about justice because so much of Rabbinic literature
and divine justice, so much of Rabbinic literature is explaining how things
fit into the divine economy of reward and punishment. You know, and
הבית המקדש HaBeit HaMikdash was destroyed because of this עון avon and
this thing happened because of that עון. avon. And sometimes what's extremely
powerful, especially in a post-Holocaust era, is where the Rabbis acknowledge that
this does not make any sense within our understanding of שכר ועונש.
sachar v'onesh. And to some point, the most fair thing we can
say is we don't understand, rather than try to attribute to God
a type of שכר ועונש sachar v'onesh which makes no sense. So,
that is some that sort of, you know, within the theological issues
of חז"ל Chazal and having everything to fit, this is very powerful
with the power of acknowledging that some things just don't fit.
Yes. חזור לאחוריך Chazor l’achorecha is an allusion to וראית את אחורי.
V’ra’ita et achorai. We can't really understand the way it operates in
tragedy. Moshe Moshe wanted to see God's face, but God said... right.
ופני לא יראו.
U’fanai
lo yeira’u.
Right.
Aha. So, you can't see... so you only get a glimpse. You
don't really see the whole... you don't have a full understanding.
That's good. Can we say that Moshe left history when Moshe goes
up there with God? He stepped out of human history. And so,
when God says look behind you, look down and, you know, you
can re-insert
yourself into history.
See, you get a glimpse of human history, but he at that
point left human history, he came so close to God. Right. He
was connected to the...
right. So, it's a chance to get back in. And that's right.
Yeah. Very nice.
But
what does the גמרא Gemara mean in the context of the earlier
where we mean, what's the message here?
Besides that he got the Torah but also this is what happened
to him? That the... But they both have the phrase כך עלה
במחשבה? Kacha ala b'machshava? Well, I think that it's sort of preparing
us theologically for this answer of we don't
understand, it's God's will, which sounds like a real punt when, you
know, it's like you're really struggling with issues of theodicy. Oh, it's
all God's will. So I think that it's sort of—it prepares the
ground for us by saying that there's sometimes, you know, good things
that are also we say are God's will that you don't really
fully understand. Why was משה Moshe זוכה zocho to the תורה Torah
if God could have given it to רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So
once we acknowledge that we're not just using this as an excuse
to deal with difficult theological challenges, you know, questions of theodicy, I
think that to some degree it helps us frame, prepare us for
the second answer. You know my theory.
No, or I think—I mean, I'm gonna think about what you said,
but there's a certain futility. And we start out with every
little—that's interesting, oh that's interesting—from omni-significant to almost haphazard and random, not
random, but haphazard. That's a great point. I hadn't thought about that
contrast. Right, that רבי עקיבא—no, Rabbi Akiva you're right, that's right. That
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva has to give meaning to everything, and in
God's world or God's תורה Torah even the little, the little crowns
on the letters have significance. But ultimately when we switch from that
תורה Torah to God's world, some things just don't make any sense,
at least to our understanding.
That's a very powerful point. But again, I'm not sure what the
larger message
is.
But it's in the text here. Right. Even makes it more prickly,
you know.
But maybe that's again
the power of תורה שבעל פה, Torah She-be'al Peh, meaning we really
are not—as human beings we really can't understand God, and we really
can't understand how the world makes sense,
you know, how do we really fully see God in the world?
Why do some people get things they don't deserve? Why do some
people get punished? That whole—so when we really sort of—we really—it would
be—it would be arrogant to think we can understand how God works
in the world. But תורה שבעל פה, Torah She-be'al Peh, we're given
the license to go ahead and interpret, you know, make order of
it, interpret everything. And that's sort of how God has brought us
in, you know, through interpreting the תורה, Torah, not through interpreting the
world.
But then we should make—do things that make sense to human beings,
not to God.
Well, that—that is a lot of what the תורה שבעל פה Torah
She-be'al Peh is about. You know, since obviously God did not intend
all of these תילי תילים tili tilim because the crowns are arbitrary,
right? So we are interpreting it, you know, very much from sort
of our human perspective and our desire to derive הלכות. halakhos. But
I like it. I mean, your point about the complete contrast about,
you know, no ability to give order in the world and then
give, you know, so immense order or meaning in every little letter.
But maybe that's exactly the point. That's a beautiful idea. Okay. So
now, alright, now to continue. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, שבע אותיות צריכות
שלשה זיונין. sheva otiyot tzrichot shlosha ziyunin. Now that we have that
wonderful מדרש, midrash, now we're going to talk about הלכה. halakha. שבע
אותיות צריכות שלשה זיונין—these sheva otiyot tzrichot shlosha ziyunin seven letters require
these three little, like, crowns, ornaments, and they are שעטנז גץ—the shatnez
gets שין, shin, עין, ayin, טית, tet, נון, nun, זין, zayin, גימל,
gimmel, צדיק. tzadik. And that's—I gave you that sampling of text. אמר
רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, חזינא להו לספרי דוקני דבי רב. hazina
lehu le-safrei dukani d'vei Rav.
I've seen these very precise ספרים sefarim in the house of רב.
Rav. דחטטי להו לגגי דחית. dekhattu lehu le-gagei d'het.
They made a—they made a bump in the top of the חית.
het. And what does that bump mean? If you look at רשי,
Rashi, he says it's sort of like the קוצו של יוד kotzo
shel yod that we were talking about. It's the little fact that—a
little thing rises—you see the חית het in רשי, Rashi, that there's
a little bit of a pointy thing that comes up at the
top of the left. Okay. You see that in the רשי? Rashi?
Okay. Okay. So that's what he said. But תוספות Tosafot says no,
חוטרא chutra is like a—what do you call it? Like a hump
of a camel. And תוספות, Tosafot, based on another גמרא, Gemara, says
that a חית het is supposed to look like two זיינין zayins
connected with a camel hump. Okay. And that's that picture in תוספות.
Tosafot. So that's what a חוטרא chutra is—it's a camel hump. If
you look at your חית het here in the picture, you see
we follow תוספות. Tosafot. If you look at the sampling of the
writing, right, it's done subtly, it's not as obvious as in תוספות.
Tosafot. So take a look at the חית. het. You see how
if you were to remove the hump, you'd get two זיינין? zayins?
Right? You see that in the sampling I handed out? Okay.
So anyway, we're just looking at תורה. Torah.
Well, I think the key word here is ספרי דוקני—very sifrei dukani
precise ones. Some were written with greater precision and greater care and
others were written a little more sloppily. Okay. So it's actually saying
there—better—so I looked at the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, but I looked
at a good one, I looked at one that was very precise.
Okay. Okay. So it had a little bump in the חית.
het. דתלי לכרעיה דהי. de-tali le-karei de-hei. And it suspended the leg
of the הי, hei, meaning the leg of the הי, hei, the
left leg, you don't want it to touch the roof, or else
it's going to be a חית, het, not a הי. hei. So
it has to be suspended in mid-air. Okay.
דחטטי להו לגגי דחית, dekhattu lehu le-gagei d'het, it made a hump
in the top of the חית. het. כלומר חי הוא ברומו של
עולם, ke-lomar Chai hu b'rumo shel olam, to point up to God.
You know, especially if you have like the little triangle like תוספות.
Tosafot. God lives up in the high. And the word חית het
is like— חיים, chayim, life. Okay, God God lived up high. דתליא
לכרעיה
דה, de-talya le-karei de-hei, it suspended the leg of the ה, hei,
the the left leg, כדבעי מיניה רב יהודה נשיאה מרב אמי, ki-de-ba'ei
mineih Rav Yehudah Nesi'ah me-Rav Ami, so we were gonna ask about
the significance of the of the picture of the ה. hei. Now
the funny thing is that presumably if you make a חית chet
without the little bump, it's still כשר. kasher. We don't know that
but we can imagine that that could be true. But if you
don't if your leg of the ה hei is connected to the
top, it's no longer a ה, hei, now a חית. chet. So
the the differences here are not necessarily of the same weight. But
anyway why is the leg of the ה hei suspended?
Like the question was asked of רב יהודה נשיאה Rav Yehudah Nesi'ah
from רב אמי. Rav Ami. מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's meant by
the verse, בטחו בה' עדי עד, bitchu ba-Hashem adei ad, trust in
God forever and ever, כי ביה ה' צור עולמים, ki be-Yah Hashem
tzur olamim, because in כה, Kah, one of God's name God, is
the rock of of the world. So what does that mean ביה,
be-Yah, with כה, Kah, with the with the name כה? Kah? So
אמר ליה, amar leih, so so he didn't understand the question. He
just said what's פשט pshat in the פסוק? pasuk? What does the
פסוק pasuk say? Trust in God. He says okay, כה תלה בטחונו
בהקדוש ברוך הוא, koh talah bit-chono ba-Kadosh Baruch Hu, she put your
faith in God, הרי זה לו מחסה בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא, harei
zeh lo machaseh ba-olam ha-zeh u-va-olam ha-ba, עולמים, olamim, maybe he thought
the question was the plural of worlds. So God will be there
will be your safeguard will be there for you in this world
and in the world to come. So that's what he thought he
was asking him. What's פשט pshat in the פסוק. pasuk. So אמר
ליה, amar leih, no no no, that wasn't my question. אנא הכי
קשיא לי, ana hachi kashya li, here was my question. מאי שנא
דכתיב ביה, mai shena de-chtiv be-Yah, it says because in כה Kah
God is צור עולמים. tzur olamim. What's the בית? beit? ולא כתיב
יה, ve-lo chtiv Yah, why doesn't it just say כה? Kah? Why
does it say trust in God because God is the rock of
ages? What's the בית? beit? With כה. Kah. So he says, ah,
כדדרש רב יהודה ברבי אלעאי. ki-de-darish Rav Yehudah be-Rabbi Ilai. רב יהודה
ברבי אלעאי Rav Yehudah be-Rabbi Ilai interprets, אלו שני עולמות, elu sheneih
olamot, the כה Kah is the יוד yud and the ה. hei.
So it's not saying God, it's saying with יוד yud and ה
hei
ה' צור עולמים. Hashem tzur olamim. God fashioned the world through the
use of the two letters of His name, the יוד yud and
the ה. hei. So how is this? אמר אלו שני עולמות שברא
הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar elu sheneih olamot she-bara ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, אחד
בה, echad be-hei, one using the ה, hei, ואחד ביוד, ve-echad be-yud,
and one using the יוד. yud. ואיני יודע אם עולם הבא ביוד
ועולם הזה בה, ve-eini yodeia im olam ha-ba be-yud ve-olam ha-zeh be-hei,
whether the future world was with the יוד yud and this world
with the ה. hei. By the way again remember that in traditional
חז"ל, Chazal, future world is not where your soul goes after you
die, future world is what happens after the after משיח Mashiach comes.
The what this world will be in the future times. Okay so
I don't know if that world was created with the יוד yud
and our world with the ה, hei, אם עולם הזה ביוד ועולם
הבא בה, im olam ha-zeh be-yud ve-olam ha-ba be-hei, or this world
was with יוד yud and the future world was with the ה.
hei. כשהוא אומר אלה תולדות השמים והארץ בהבראם, ke-she-hu omer eileh toldot
ha-shamayim ve-ha-aretz be-hibaram, these are the stories of the heavens and the
earth when they were created, right right at the beginning of בראשית.
Bereishit. So the ה hei in בהבראם be-hibaram when God created them
is small and therefore the דרשה drashah is אל תקרי בהבראם, al
tikrei be-hibaram, in their creating, אלא בה' בראם, ela be-hei bara'am, God
created them with the letter ה, hei, בה'
בראם. be-hei bara'am. So this world was created in the ה, hei,
the future world would be with the יוד. yud. הוי אומר עולם
הזה בה, hevei omer olam ha-zeh be-hei, this world was created with
the ה, hei, ועולם הבא ביוד, ve-olam ha-ba be-yud, and the future
world in the יוד. yud. ומפני מה, u-mipnei mah, now what's the
meaning of all this?
נברא עולם הזה בה, nivra olam ha-zeh be-hei, why was this world
created with the ה? hei? What's the symbolism of that? מפני שדומה
לאכסדרה.
mipnei she-domeh le-achsadrah.
ה hei is like a courtyard, a portico. What? Yeah.
So a ה hei has like three walls right? and it's open
on the fourth wall like they would have a אכסדרה achsadrah which
you enter into a house you first have this, we mentioned that
before, this
אכסדרה. achsadrah. שכל הרוצה לצאת יצא, she-kol ha-rotzeh la-tzet yetzei, but of
course now viewing it as the exit door which is anybody that's
not interested in really making, you know, trying to toil in this
world and wants to instead just, you know, quickly get to גיהנום
Gehenom essentially is the point here, you know, and not so okay,
there's a big door on the bottom for anybody, it's like a
big trapdoor for anybody who wants to leave, be my guest, go
ahead and leave. Okay, you can go ahead and waste your world
if you want to. Okay however, ומאי טעמא
תליא כרעיה, u-mai ta'ama talya kareia, and why though is the little
you know leg of the ה hei suspended?
דהדר בתשובה, de-hadar bi-tshuvah, if you want to enter back into this
world you want to do תשובה teshuvah and really make a serious
go of things in terms of your role in this world, מעיילי
ליה, me-aylei leih, you can sneak back through the back door. Okay
so we've got a big open door policy except the open door
policy is really an open exit door policy. Okay we're not going
to stop anybody that wants to waste their life, the door's open,
be my guest, leave. Okay but there's a back door is that
you can come back in if you do תשובה. teshuvah. So real
small though you have to work a little harder, you have to
maybe climb up the leg of ה hei to get back in,
but there's a back door to come back in. Okay. ולא עיילי
בהך, ve-la aylei be-hach, so why not go back through that big
open door you left? סייעא דמילתא, saya de-milta,
things won't work out so well if you try to retrace your
footstep. Okay what? Road
traffic.
Okay. כדריש לקיש, ki-de-Resh Lakish, as ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says, דאמר
ריש לקיש, de-amar Resh Lakish, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says, מאי דכתיב,
mai de-chtiv,
what's meant by the verse, אם ללצים הוא יליץ, im la-leitzim hu
yalitz, if one
is for mockers God will sort of mock or skeptics, וענווים, va-anivim,
those that are humble, יתן חן, yiten chen, God will give grace,
kindness. בא לטהר, Ba litaher, if you're humble and you're trying to
do the right thing, מסייעין אותו, mesayyin oto, God will help you
out. בא לטמא, Ba litaame, if however you're trying to do the
wrong thing and you're coming to impure yourself, פותחין לו, potchin lo,
God's not literally going to help you do the wrong thing but
he's not going to close the door. You want it, the door's
open. You want to go do something wrong? Be my guest, okay?
He's not going to stand in your way. Now what does it
have to do about going back to the same ה? hei? So
Rashi says here, where is it? מסייעין אותו
אלמא בא לסיוע.
mesayyin oto alma ba
l'siyua.
So Rashi just gives an indirect proof that if God needs to
help you when you're doing the right thing, so you're not just
going back through the same door you came, you've got to climb
up that harder ladder to get into that back door which requires
סיוע. siyu'a. But presumably the point also is, you know, it's a
psychological point, which is if you really want to start changing your
behaviors, it's not just putting yourself back into the exact same scenarios
you had been in before and just say, oh, by force of
will I'm going to make everything better now. If you really want
to have another serious go about it, you have to find a
new way to approach things and that's the whole idea. But that
needs help because it's hard, right? It's hard to start things afresh
and approach things from a whole new way, and that's the, you
know, מסייעין אותו, mesayyin oto, you need God's help. Okay. So ומאי
טעמא אית ליה תגא? u-mai ta'ama it lei taga? And now why
does the ה hei have a little תגא, taga, have a little
like crown? Now it's not the שעטנז גץ sh'atnez getz because it's
not those are the big crowns, but this is a little thing.
Tosafot it points to the קוץ kotz of the י. yud. We've
had the קוץ kotz of the י, yud, the קוץ kotz of
the ח, chet, now we have the קוץ kotz of the ה,
hei, right? At the top left, a little point goes up. Why
is that there? ומאי טעמא אית ליה תגא אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא
u-mai ta'ama it lei taga Amar Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu says אם חוזר
בו, im chozer bo, if this person is doing תשובה teshuvah and
trying to get back into the top door, אני קושר לו קשר,
ani kosher lo kesher, I will throw him a rope. Okay? Meaning
I'll tie a knot. So it could be like he's giving you
a little crown, but I imagine it more like you have to
scale the wall there and get to get into that door, so
God's sort of reaching out His hand and throwing you the rope
to help you scale up to get back into that little door.
Okay, so again you have God tying the knot, but it was
not the knot of the crowns from before.
Okay. ומפני
מה, u-mipnei mah, but look at the side of the גרסה, girsa,
it does connect it, אני קושר לו כתר. ani kosher lo keter.
Do you see it at that little left hand column? Some replace
it to a קשר kesher with the word כתר, keter, a crown,
which is exactly back to God tying the crowns on the letter
and it's sort of like I'll give him status, acknowledgement, reward and
so on. מפני מה נברא עולם הבא ביו"ד? Mipnei mah nivra Olam
Ha-Ba be-yud? And why is the future world with a י? yud?
מפני שהצדיקים שבו מועטים, mipnei she-ha-tzaddikim she-bo mu'atim, because the future world
is going to be a lot less populated than this world. It's
a tiny little י. yud. Okay, there are not many people will
be of the future world, there will be a much the numbers
will be small. ומפני מה
כפוף ראשו? u-mipnei mah kaffuf rosho? And why is the head like
a little bit bent in the י? yud? I'm not exactly sure,
but I mean if you imagine that most of it is bent,
if you imagine it looks like a person, right? So most letters
the weight is on the bottom and they have some head, but
the י yud is like the whole thing, like it's a little
leg and the whole thing is bent over. Yeah, basically. So why
does it look like that? מפני שהצדיקים שבו כפוף ראשיהם, mipnei she-ha-tzaddikim
she-bo kaffuf rosheihem, because their heads are bent over, they're humble. Okay,
not only humble, I feel also they don't want to be jealous.
מפני מעשיהם שאינם דומים זה לזה. mipnei ma'aseihem she-einam domim zeh la-zeh.
Their actions are not similar to one another, which Rashi says means
that like if you look at Rashi here, וכבוד של
זה מרובה משל זה משום הכי והיו כפופים דמתבייש מחבירו,
u-chevod shel zeh
merubeh mi-shel zeh mishum hachi ve-hayu kfufim de-mitbayesh me-chaveiro, that even if
everybody's צדיקים, tzaddikim, there's some greater צדיק tzaddik and lesser צדיק, tzaddik,
and so you don't want to be shamed because you're humble, rather
than being arrogant that you're one of the few people that made
it to עולם הבא Olam Ha-Ba and you're one of the צדיקים,
tzaddikim, right? You actually are ashamed, like look at that guy, look
how much more he accomplished than I did, and you're going to
be embarrassed. So because of that you look down. Yeah.
Wait, I missed it.
What do you mean created the worlds as a letter?
It means that the symbolism of the letter the okay, on the
one hand because these י yud and the ה, hei, you did
miss it, I didn't really say it. The י yud and the
ה hei are letters of God's names. So it basically means I
think means that just that God is a creator, but it speaks
to sort of God's immanence in the world. Like the very world
is created by God's name. So first of all that's one message.
But then the specific use of the letter is the sense about
like how does what are the metaphysical realities upon which the world
operates?
So if the world's created with the ה hei of God's name,
then the metaphysical reality that this world operates in is it's easy
to throw your life away, but there's always an opportunity for תשובה
teshuvah but it requires effort. And the metaphysical reality of the world
to come is that it's a lot harder to
get in, you know, it's a much smaller space and that's something
that requires much more achievement in order to go in. But you're
right, I did. Okay, so ליאורה, Liora, okay, אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, הני תרי מילי
אמר רב בספרים דתניא תיובתא.
hani tere milei amar
Rav besfarim detanya tyuvta.
So after that amazing, you know, midrashic, now we get back to
some hard, hard nuts and bolts הלכה. halacha. Okay, so the following
two things רב Rav said relating to דברי תורה, divrei Torah, and
we taught a ברייתא braita that is a contradiction. חדא דאמר רב,
Chada de'amar Rav, one is what רב Rav said, ספר תורה שיש
בו שתי טעויות בכל דף ודף יתקן. Sefer Torah sheyesh bo shtei
ta'uyot bechol daf vadaf yitaken. If a ספר תורה Sefer Torah has
two mistakes in every column, a דף daf here does not mean
a what do you call it, a full page that's called a
יריעה, yeriyah, the entire קלפים klafim that you know are sewn together,
but a דף daf here means a column. עמוד, Amud, we know,
we normally call an עמוד amud a column, we have an עמוד
א amud aleph and an עמוד ב. amud bet. But that's very
interesting. An עמוד amud does not mean the side of the page,
it means literally a column like an עמוד amud is a column
of a building, which is why in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, for example,
you have when people are giving, you know, where something is located
in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, the traditional printing of the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, they
will say א ב ג aleph bet gimel or ד. dalet. What
the heck is עמוד ג amud gimel or ד? dalet? Do they
have like a rectangle of something? No, because it was printed with
two columns on side א aleph and two columns on side ב.
bet. So עמוד amud actually means a column and in this context
דף daf also means a column. Okay, so if your ספר תורה
Sefer Torah has three has,
he said has, two errors in every column then you can still
fix it. However, if it's so קרוע, karua, so you know poorly
done that it has שלוש, shalosh, three errors in every column, then
it is, then you יגנז. yiganez. Put it in שמות. sheimos. It's
not כבוד kavod to take out a ספר תורה Sefer Torah that
has that many corrections in it. דתניא תיובתא, Detanya tyuvta, we taught
a contradiction that a ברייתא, braita, same idea but goes, but is
a little more lenient. שלוש יתקן, Shalosh yitaken, three mistakes in every
column you can fix. ארבע יגנז, Arba yiganez, four mistakes in every
column you have to put it in שמות. sheimos. תנא, Tana, we
taught in a ברייתא, braita, אם יש בו דף אחת שלמה מטלת
על כולה. im yesh bo daf achat shleimah matelet al kulah. However,
if you have one perfect column, okay, that has no mistakes, it
can, you know, it can go a long way. It can make,
oh it's not like this is a terribly a completely terrible ספר
תורה Sefer Torah to put in שמות sheimos as one. No, if
one is good, then we can more tolerate some of the other
problems and fix them. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is of course
going to be how perfect does the perfect one have to be?
Yeah, that is a continuing our central theme of מעכב? me'akev?
Oh that's an interesting point.
I don't think so because מעכב me'akev actually means if something is
wrong can you just go on without it? Right here you're actually
fixing it. So the question is more like how much is it
just such a problem that even if you fixed it, we don't,
it's like, you know,
it's I don't think it's exactly the מעכב. me'akev. מעכב me'akev is
you don't have it, it's still good. Here you are going to
fix it, but maybe it's not good anyway because it just was
so filled with mistakes, you know.
Okay, so now the תיבעי ליה לרבי יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא.
Tiba'i leh leRabbi Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta. Yeah. But the צדיק
tzaddik in עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, you know, maybe there are people
greater than him. Maybe, you know, he has many flaws also but
that one good thing about him, one good דף, daf, that's how
he's
Very nice.
So even if you have a lot of things that need fixing
through the rest of you, there's one ah beautiful. I think we
got people. I think we brought
people's נחת רוח.
nachat ruach. די דיינו. Dai Dayenu. Okay, ושפחה בישא. Veshifcha bisha. Exactly.
This is איפה.
eifo. Absolutely true. Okay. אמר רב זביד בר שמואל, Amar Rav Zvid
bar Shmuel, רב יהודה בר שמואל Rav Yehuda bar Shmuel said, okay,
we got to get a little make a little more distance here,
בר מרשא משמיה דרב bar Marsha mishmei deRav in the name of
רב, Rav, והוא דכתיב רוביה דספרא שפיר. Vehu dechtiv rubya desaphra shapir.
When do we say that you can tolerate these mistakes or one
will save the rest? If most of the ספר sefer is written
correctly. Now what does it mean if most of the ספר sefer
is written correctly? If most of the ספר sefer is written correctly,
then it's not true that you've got mistakes in every single column.
So one minute.
I have to look this up beforehand. The ראש Rosh says, or
he
understands this just one second.
I'm trying to
you know what, let's go on. I'm not I'm trying to remember.
The ראש Rosh has a discussion about this. What does it matter,
you know, how do you basically say both things? If it's mistakes
in every single column, then you can't have רובו דספרא rubo desaphra
written correctly. Unless it's saying that you need
both, that רוב rov needs to be correct and
then even if the then it's the minority of all the minority,
every one of the minority has a mistake. I'll have to double-check.
I think he says you need both things, רוב rov has to
be correct and then even if the minority of all the minority,
every one of the minority has a mistake.
Anyway, okay, but it's obviously hemming it in even more. Alright, let's
keep on going and it says like this: איבעיא להו לרבי יצחק
בר שמואל בר מרתא אי הך דף שלש טעויות מאי. Ibeia lehu
le-Rabbi Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta ee hach daf shalosh tauyos mai.
Let's say that one column that was perfect that saved everything else,
that itself has three errors? Three errors you're allowed to fix. So
it's not perfect, it's just not hitting the four problem. So what's
the הלכה? halacha? אמר ליה הואיל ואשתרי
לתיקוני מתקני. Amar lei hoil ve-ishtarei letikuni matkanei. Since it was under
four, it was three, and it allowed the number that you're allowed
to fix, you're allowed to fix up to three, then it is
considered to save the whole rest of the ספר תורה. sefer Torah.
So we are on the one hand we're being stricter that you
need רוב rov of the ספר sefer to be written correctly, to
be written without mistakes, but we're also being a little bit more
lenient that this one column that saves the rest doesn't have to
be completely perfect, but it can have as long as it has
no more than three mistakes. And now we go on: והני מילי
בחסרות. Ve-hanei mili be-chaserot.
And when are the problems? When the problems are that letters are
lacking, because if you're lacking a letter, what do you have to
do to fix it? You have to scrape away the whole word
and rewrite the word again in smaller letters. That's a big fixing.
אבל ביתירות, Aval be-yeterot, if there's an extra letter, לית לן
בה, leit lan bah, it's not a problem, which does not mean
תוספות Tosafot says that you don't have to worry about extra letters,
but it just means you're not doing as radical of a fix.
Scraping away an extra letter is not going to look as bad
as scraping away the whole thing. I have to say that the
way they write the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, and I'm familiar with
this now because we hire a סופר sofer regularly to write the
קלפים klafim for our students,
you can't tell that they have... I'll see a problem and I'll
say, you got this word totally wrong, and I'm saying to myself,
how's he going to squeeze in the extra יוד, yod, how's it
going to look so sloppy? If he does it, you can never
tell that the thing was scraped away and corrected because the way
they use the ink on the... the type of ink they use,
the parchment that they use, you can scrape it away and it's
like it's completely invisible. You don't even see that something had been
written on it. But the גמרא Gemara I think was concerned that
there would be some type of marks left, and therefore the marks
are much greater if you have to scrape away the whole word
and fit in a missing letter than if you just have to
scrape away an extra letter.
And now we go on: והני מילי
יתירות אבל בחסרות מאי קיימא
לן? Ve-hanei mili yeterot aval be-chaserot mai
kayma lan?
And what's the problem
if letters or words were missing? Because אמר רב חננאל משום רב
כמנומר. Amar Rav Chananel mishum Rav kemenumar. It looks like a leopard.
They were spotted. So if you're going to have to do a
lot of scrapings away and three or four fixes on every single
column and it's not just taking away an extra letter, it's scraping
away the whole word and writing the word again, then that's going
to really be a not appropriate ספר תורה sefer Torah and therefore
you should just put the whole thing in גניזה. geniza. We're going
to continue with this but I did want to say one other
point by the way that I forgot to mention and it's really...
you've spoken about this... this קוצו של יוד kotzo shel yod story,
right? Are these issues of the letters a similar issue when you're
dealing with not ספרי תורה, sifrei Torah, תפילין tefillin and מזוזות? mezuzot?
The context sounds highly, one that is highly ritualized ספרים. sefarim. So
if you look at this little תוספות Tosafot on כט עמוד א,
kaf tet amud aleph, זיל אייתי ינוקא דלא חכים ולא טיפש. zil
aytei yanuka d'la chakim v'la tipesh. He says like this, the first
תוספות Tosafot on כט עמוד א: kaf tet amud aleph: מעשה היה
בגט. Ma'aseh haya be-get. There was a story with a גט get
שהיה דל"ת שלו כדמות יו"ד. she-haya dalet shelo kidmut yod.
The דל"ת dalet almost looked like a
יוד. yod. Would you have to use a קטן, katan, would you
have to identify it as a דל"ת dalet as opposed to יוד?
yod? So it says והביאו לפני רבינו אליהו ינוקא דלא חכים ולא
טיפש וקראו כדת. ve-heviu lifnei Rabbeinu Eliyahu yanuka d'la chakim v'la tipesh
ve-karo kedat. So they brought this minor to read it and he
read it correctly. He read it, he didn't just identify the letter,
he read it in context, he read the whole word כדת. kedat.
והכשירו מהא דשמעתא. ve-hechshiro me-ha deshmatta. And he said it was כשר
kosher based on this גמרא. Gemara.
Which basically seems to say that you need to follow the same
rules. But again remember, that's where the problem was the basic shape
of the word, is it a יוד yod or is it a
דל"ת? dalet? If like the other rules like מוקף גויל, mukaf gvil,
קוצו של יוד, kotzo shel yod, that's not so clear and that's
interesting what exactly...
They
go insane, of course. And this holds up as he's sitting and
writing a גט get and everything to a סופר. sofer.
I can imagine. Okay, so now כט עמוד ב. kaf tet amud
bet. איגרא חמוה דרבי אבא. Igra chamuh de-Rabbi Abba.
איגרא, Igra, the father-in-law of רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, הוה ליה יתירות
בספריה. hava lei yeterot be-sifrei. He had extra letters in his ספרים,
sefarim, which we talked before not a big deal, scrape it away
it doesn't make the ספר sefer look too bad. אתא לקמיה דרבי
אבא. Ata lekamei de-Rabbi Abba. He came to רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba,
his son-in-law. אמר ליה. Amar lei. So רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said
don't worry about it. לא אמרן אלא בחסירות. Lo amran ela be-chaserot.
When do we say having a lot of mistakes is the problem
and we won't even let you fix it? If it is things,
letters are missing, because then you have to do a lot of
scraping. אבל ביתירות, Aval be-yeterot, in your case even presumably if there
were a lot of extra letters or it was throughout the ספר,
sefer, לית לן בה, leit lan bah, it is not a big
deal, we allow for corrections, it doesn't look so bad.
תוספות Tosafot says some people mistakenly think this גמרא Gemara means you
don't have to correct it if it's an extra letter. That's not
what it's saying, it's saying we can correct it but we don't
have to worry that we have to do a lot.
Yeah what if a ספר sefer is just used for studying now
as opposed to פרשה בשבת? parsha be-shabbos? Right right yeah so yeah
here
the assumption is that we're just talking about a regular ספר. sefer.
Now there is a concern in הלכה halacha even if you only
want to use it for studying are we concerned that if it's
not מוגה mugah and if it's not correct that you might accidentally
come to use it for a ritual context? But the assumption here
is you want to use it for ritual context. Okay yeah. All
right so now we have ten minutes to do today's דף. daf.
All right.
When should we take it tomorrow before שול? shul?
When is it? Between מנחה Mincha and מעריב Maariv yeah. Okay unless
we want to do it twice because we are really a full
דף daf behind. Is anybody up for that like before מנחה Mincha
maybe between מנחה Mincha and מעריב? Maariv? Why don't we do that
because we're really I mean we're almost a full דף daf behind
we might as well make it up.
Or we have to tell?
I'll tell them. Oh you'll take care of it? Okay fine. Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אידך דאמר רב Idach de-amar
Rav so that was one teaching of רב Rav which was three
or four mistakes in every single column. What was the other teaching
of רב? Rav? That רב Rav said by ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah
הכותב ספר תורה בא לגמור גומר ואפילו באמצע הדף. hakoseiv Sefer Torah
ba ligmor gomer ve-afilu be-emtza hadaf.
When you're writing your ספר תורה Sefer Torah and you come to
the last פסוק pasuk okay you know סופרים sofrim not only they
have to do the individual writing correctly they've got to plan well
in advance because they need the לעיני כל ישראל le-einei kol Yisrael
to be at the bottom of a column. Not only that there
are some things like the שירת הים Shiras ha-Yam and האזינו Haazinu
that you have to get them you know exact and start them
in a particular place in the column. So you have to plan
in advance. So he's saying what if you didn't plan in advance
and here you are you got לעיני כל ישראל le-einei kol Yisrael
and you're at the top of a column? Are you allowed to
end a ספר תורה Sefer Torah at the top of a column?
So he said yes ובגומר ואפילו באמצע הדף u-vgomer va-afilu be-emtza hadaf
you can end even in the middle of a column. מתיבי Meisivei
I ask against it we have a ברייתא braisa from מסכת סופרים
Masechet Sofrim הכותב ספר תורה בא לגמור לא יגמור באמצע הדף כדרך
שגומר בחומשין.
hakoseiv Sefer
Torah
ba ligmor lo yigmor be-emtza hadaf kederech she-gomar be-Chumashin. You're writing and
you're coming to the end. לא יגמור באמצע הדף lo yigmor be-emtza
hadaf don't end in the middle of a column כדרך שגומר בחומשין
kederech she-gomar be-Chumashin like you would do in a חומש. Chumash. A
חומש Chumash by the way in the time before the printing press
was basically a codex. It was like scribed on parchment but it
was random access you know I mean that's the problem with the
scroll you got like when we used to have cassette tapes instead
of CD-ROMs right? So what they would do is that they would
bind it into a book but it would still be scribed actually
where they had that amazing you know thing when was that the
guy finding the library
you know whatever anyway you could see these gorgeous you know codices
which were scribed and the כתב ksav was beautiful and was on
קלף klaf but it was made as a codex made as a
bound book. Okay so that was חומשין Chumashin that could not be
used you know obviously for ritual purposes. There actually is a position
of the רמב"ם Rambam that said that if you don't have a
ספר תורה Sefer Torah you can read from a חומש Chumash that
type of a חומש Chumash at least in שול. shul. That it's
only a כבוד הציבור kevod hatzibur issue and if there's no option
you can even read from at least a handwritten חומש Chumash in
the שול. shul. Anyway so presumably when you end a חומש Chumash
you didn't have to end at the end of a column you
would end wherever you would end. So it says maybe you could
do the same when you're writing a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. לא
יגמור באמצע הדף כדרך שגומר בחומשין. lo yigmor be-emtza hadaf kederech she-gomar
be-Chumashin. Do not end in the middle of a column אלא מקצר
והולך עד סוף הדף. ela mekatzer ve-holech ad sof hadaf.
You have to get to the end of a column even if
it means that your lines will slowly get shorter and shorter and
shorter but you have to get to the bottom and you have
a nice little מקצר mekatzer and. Okay now of course that means
that you have enough lines left. If you would have ended in
the middle plan from the beginning and eventually you can get to
the bottom. But if you would have ended in three lines at
the top you're not going to anyway get to the bottom. So
you got to really plan in advance. Very long lines right?
Well we're going to get we're going actually get to that possibility
in a minute. Okay so anyway this is a contradiction of רב.
Rav. So the גמרא Gemara says because רב Rav says you can
end in the middle כי קאמר רב בחומשין. ki ka-amar Rav be-Chumashin.
When רב Rav said end in the middle he meant a חומש.
Chumash. Now
of course that's already funny since when would there be ritual laws
of a חומש? Chumash?
It does but this shows you that when you're writing it on
קלף klaf and especially according to the רמב"ם Rambam that things you
could read from חומשים Chumashim and חומשים Chumashim have קדושה kedusha
you know and they start talking about stacking books and so on
when it's written handwritten on קלף klaf it had a certain you
know religious weight even if it wasn't used in the שול. shul.
So there could actually be rules of how do you write in
חומשים.
Chumashim. They copy the new book they copy the old right? So
they didn't necessarily have to copy from a valid ספר תורה Sefer
Torah underneath.
Oh that's interesting. We actually פוסק pasken that you do copy from
a valid ספר תורה Sefer Torah but whether that would have been
strictly necessary is a good point. Right. Okay so anyway so when
did רב Rav say you could end in the middle of a
column? By a
חומש. Chumash. אסיפר תורה קאמר A-Sefer Torah ka-amar רב Rav says if
you're writing a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. It says okay חומשים של
ספר תורה Chumashim shel Sefer Torah which means the חמישה חומשי תורה.
Chamisha Chumshei Torah. When you end בראשית Bereishis you don't have to
end it at the bottom of a column. And if you know
we don't do that. We end בראשית Bereishis wherever we end it
we have four blank lines and then we start שמות. Shemos. And
we end שמות Shemos wherever we end it and we have four
blank lines and we start ויקרא. Vayikra. So when you come to
end one ספר sefer of the five ספרים sfarim of the ספרי
תורה Sifrei Torah you can end in the middle of a column.
Okay, אין ain is it true? אמר רב יהושע בר אבא, Amar
Rav Yehoshua bar Abba, אמר רב גידל, Amar Rav Gidel, אמר רב,
Amar Rav, לעיני כל ישראל Le’einei Koysrael באמצע הדף. be’emtza hadaf.
That's pretty explicit. You can have the word לעיני כל ישראל Le’einei
Koysrael in the middle of a column, which sounds like the original
teaching of רב, Rav, you don't have to go to the bottom
of the column. So the גמרא Gemara says ההיא באמצע שיטה איתמר.
Hahi be’emtza shita itmar.
He did not mean, although it's not what he says, he did
not mean the middle of a column, he meant the middle of
a line. You have to end it at the bottom of the
column, but you don't have to end it at the end of
the line. You know, as when you write actually כתבא, ksava, right,
you know at the bottom it's like, you know, הכל שריר וקיים,
hakol sharir vekayam,
those three words can take up this much space because you want
to have it like right and left justified, end at the end
of the line. So here it's saying you don't have to do
that. לעיני כל ישראל Le’einei Koysrael can end at the middle of
a line, but it has to be at the bottom of a
column. Okay, now the גמרא's Gemara going to quote a debate about
that.
איתמר, Itmar, רבנן אמרי Rabbanan amri אף באמצע שיטה.
af be’emtza shita.
It can end even in the middle of a line, which presumably
means not only in the middle of a column, but even in
the middle of a line. רב אשי אמר באמצע שיטה דווקא. Rav
Ashi amar be’emtza shita davka. No, only in the middle of a
line, that's okay, but it has to end at the bottom of
a column. This is all really about the aesthetics, right? It's a,
it's a beauty thing,
it's
got to go to the bottom. Maybe you say, you know, the
line doesn't have to be left justified, but the column has to
go to the bottom. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, okay, והלכתא,
Vahilchasa, and the הלכה halacha is באמצע שיטה דווקא. be’emtza shita davka.
We allow you to end in the middle of a sentence לעיני
כל ישראל, Le’einei Koysrael, but we do not allow you to end
in the middle of a column, and you have to plan ahead
to get the last, you know, end of the ספר תורה Sefer
Torah to be at the bottom of the column. And later we're
going to talk about what happens if you have to write really
big letters in order to make that happen.
Okay, so we will end here for today.
והלכתא. Vahilchasa.